Guide to the Tanzania Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Tanzania collection
1873-2010
1910-1991
MS 1545
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9.75
(12 boxes)
The collection consists of printed material relating to political, economic, and social conditions in Tanzania. Photographs and textiles are also included.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator.
Associated Materials
African Collection (MS 605); Pamphlet Collection (MS 1351); African Postcard Collection (MS 1575). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of printed material relating to political, economic, and social conditions in Tanzania. Photographs and textiles are also included.
Arrangement
The material in the original accession is arranged chronologically, with photographs last. Additions to the collection may vary in arrangement.
Ngorongoro Crater (Tanzania) -- Antiquities; Tanzania -- Description and travel; Tanzania -- Economic conditions; Tanzania -- Politics and government; Tanzania -- Rural conditions; Tanzania -- Social conditions; Photographs -- Tanzania; Kikwete, Jakaya Khalfan Mrisho, 1950-; Nyerere, Julius K., 1922-1999; Chama cha Mapinduzi; National Development Corporation (Tanzania)
- Inventory
  - "Arusha: A Brochure of the Northern Province and its Capital Town": commemoration of the first session of the legislative council of the Tanganyika Territory, 1929 December 5 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "The Silver Jubilee of H. H. the Sultan of Zanzibar" and related materials, 1937, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Clove Growers Association of Zanzibar: brochures, statements, 1951, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Tanganyika: general information pamphlets; brochures; booklets from the Tanganyika Information Services (TIS) and the Dar es Salaam City Council, 1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Kivukoni College: information booklets, journals, 1962-1963, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Tanganyikan: journal of the T.S.D.G. [Tanganyikan Students for a Democratic Government?], Makerere University College, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Government papers: constitution, reports, amendments, 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Science/technology (Dar es Salaam Technical College, Tanzania Commission for Science and Technology, Tanzania National Scientific Research Council): magazines, bulletins, statements, [1964?], 1981, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Education: journals, bulletins, printed materials, 1965, 1976, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Mission to the United Nations, a news service, 1965 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - USUDIA: magazine of the University Students Union, Dar es Salaam, [1965?] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Tanzanian Police Department: journal, [1965?] (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Nyerere, Julius K., former president of Tanzania: papers, interviews, 1967, 1977, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - General information pamphlets; brochures; booklets; calendars, 1968, 1979, 1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Afro-Shirazi Party (ASP): reports on the Zanzibar revolution, 1970-1971, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "The Mirror of Language," The Committee on the Swahili Language, Dar es Salaam University, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Economic affairs/commerce: papers, regulations, 1972-1974, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Newspapers, 1974-1979 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Agrarian and rural development: magazines, research papers, Dar es Salaam University, 1977-1979, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Mshindi, Ugamaa Leo, Ulatati: magazines in the Swahili language, 1977-1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Bilal Muslim Mission of Tanzania: journal, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - "Ijtemah," [Iftitah] ceremony of the Dawoodi Bohra Jamaats, 1978 April 29-May 1 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "Amboni Yetu," Amboni Estate Ltd., Africa Office, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - National Institute of Transport and Tanzania Harbours Authority: programs, journals, 1979, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Khadija: The Queen of the Arabs, by Akberali G. Dharsi, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Political magazines, 1980-1988 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs: newsletters, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Britain-Tanzania Society: bulletins, 1982, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Capital Development Authority (CDA): pamphlets, reports, 1988, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - "Haki na Amani": Benedictine Publications, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - "Zanzibar Newsletter" (incorporating 'Free Zanzibar Voice'), 1990 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - United Nations Development Programme (UNDP): documentation, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Tanzania Media Women's Association (TAMWA): magazine, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Zanzibar, general information pamphlets, Undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - "The Tragedy of Zanzibar," by A. S. Kharusi, Zanzibar Organization, Undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - College of Business Education (CBE): magazine, Undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - "Elephant Hunting Expedition: German East Africa": photograph album with map and text, 1910-1911 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - "National dance ('Ngoma Khu')" by Wa-Swahili women, E. Africa, Underwood and Underwood Publishers: 2 photographs, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Photograph album: Tanzania, Egypt, Kenya, Mozambique, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Photographs
    General
    See also: folder 31, Kenya Collection, Manuscript Group Number 1523
- Additional Material, Accession 1996-M-039
  - Additional printed materials/ephemera, 1960-1965, 1977-1986, 1995 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 1999-M-023
  - Additional printed materials, 1922, 1929-1930, 1938-1939, 1947-1958, 1980, 1992 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2000-M-037
  - African Adult Education Association (AAEA), "Newsletter", no. 2, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chama Cha Mapinduzi (CCM)
    - "Address by Mwalimu J. K. Nyerere, Chairman of Chama Cha Mapinduzi at the opening of the National Conference Dodoma, 22nd October 1987", 1987 October 22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Tuimarishe CCM", 1989 March
  - Hopkins, Raymond F., International Development Research Center, "Constituency Ties and Deviant Expectations Among Tanzanian Legislators", 1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Leakey, M. D., "Excavation of Burial Mounds in Ngorongoro Crater," reprinted from Tanzania Notes and Records, no. 66, December 1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Non-Governmental Organisations Coordinating Committee (NGOCC), "NGOCC Newsletter," no. 3, 1996 September-1997 January (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Research on Poverty Alleviation (REPOA), "REPOA Newsletter," no. 1, 1995 January-June (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Rizvi, Sayyid Saeed Akhtar, chief missionary, "Your Questions Answered," vol. 4, 1975 April-1978 June (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Schatte, Hans-Gerd, "Die Frau in Tanzania", 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Tanzania Voters' Manifesto for Gender Equality" [English summary of original document in Kiswahili], [1999] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The United Republic of Tanzania, "A Guide for Diplomatic Missions", 1990 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - United States International Communication Agency (USICA) Workshop, "Seminar Review", 1979 November 12-30 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs of the sultan of the Chaga Tribe in German military dress and Masai warriors, [ca. 1890] (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Additional Material, Accession 2002-M-080
  - Beit al-Ajaib, the House of Wonders, Zanzibar [includes photograph], Circa 1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Civic United Front (CUF) [includes clothing], [199-] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Travel guide to Dar es Salaam, Circa 1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of street scenes of Zanzibar, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Graphic [illustrations re slave trade, scenes of Zanzibar], 1873 March 29, 1882 January 28 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Additional Material, Accession 2007-M-017
  Scope and Contents
  This accession consists of printed campaign materials and ephemera pertaining to the candidacy of Jakaya Kikwete (Chama cha Mapinduzi Party) in the 2005 Tanzanian presidential election.
  - "Ilani Ya Uchaguzi Ya CCM Kwa Ajili Ya Uchaguzi Mkuu Wa Mwaka", 2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clothing, includes cap, polo shirt, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Fabric [most likely used as banners and/or clothing], 2005 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Posters, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Additional Material, 1960-2005; Accession 2010-M-117
  Arrangement
  The material is arranged as received.
  - Publications
    - "Why Tansanian students were expelled", 1978
    - Debemoja (Special Issue, 1970-Tanzania's year of decision) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Twende (Minaki Secondary School Magazine), 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Gender Statistics and Related Issues, 1997 annual publication by the Bureau of Statistics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Women Development for Science and Technology Association (WODSTA), 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Posters, Circa 2005
    - "Legal and human rights promotion 10 year anniversary", 2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Ndugu Zangu Ukweli Ndio Huu", Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Pambazuko la Katiba Mpya", Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Ndugu Ali Hassan Mwinyi", Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Mhe. Benjamin William Mkapa", Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photograph
    - Masai visit a rural medical center in the Northern Province, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Additional material, 1969-2010; Accession 2015-M-001
  - Printed material, 1969-2010 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Photographs, 1970, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Printed fabric remnant, Circa 1971 (Box 2)
  - Posters, Circa 2000s (Folder 3)